Beth: A range of strategies can
be used to support communication
and social interaction let’s
look at these in more detail.
Joe: PECS is a unique
alternative/augmentative communication
system that works for children who
do not speak, who are unintelligible
or who are minimal communicators.
It consists of six phases and begins by
teaching an individual to give a single
picture of a desired item or action to a
“communicative partner” who immediately
honours the exchange as a request.
The system goes on to teach
discrimination of pictures and how
to put them together in ‘sentences’
and may in fact allow learners to
develop speech by transitioning onto
a speech generating device [SGD].
Beth: Makaton is a language programme
using symbols, signs and speech in spoken
word order, to enable communication.
Signing can help those with no speech, or
those whose speech is unclear and helps
provide extra clues to what is being said.
Symbols can help with limited speech
and cannot or prefer not to sign.
Makaton takes away the frustration and
enables individuals to connect with
other people and the world around them.
Joe: Social stories can
help autistic people develop
greater social understanding.
They are short descriptions of
a particular situation, event
or activity, and what to expect
in that situation and why.
Social stories can be used to develop
self-care skills such as how to clean
teeth, social skills like saying
thank you, and academic abilities.
They present information in a literal way,
which may improve a person's understanding
of a difficult situations or activities.
Beth: Music cues can be used for children
with autism as they seem to respond to
emotions conveyed through music better
than to other forms of communication.
Engaging with music is thought to
help children become more flexible,
responsive and attentive, leading to
better social and communication skills.
Joe: Comic strip conversations are simple
visual representations of conversation.
They show the things that are
actually said in a conversation,
how people might be feeling, what
people's intentions might be.
Comic strip conversations use stick
figures and symbols to represent
social interactions and abstract
aspects of conversation, and
colour to represent the emotional
content of a statement or message.
Beth: Visual supports and technology
can be used as communication
tools in most situations, and
are adaptable and often portable.
They help to provide structure
and routine and improve
understanding, avoiding frustration.
Visual supports can be real objects of
reference or tactile objects, for example
food labels, pictures, models, coloured
squares, symbols or written words.
They can also be created using
technology, showing photographs, short
videos, pictures and symbols or actions
on a smartphone, tablet or computer.
Visual supports however are very
personal and what works for one
person may not work for another.